Waldo Peirce Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Waldo Peirce Papers 1889-1985
MSS47977
Peirce, Waldo, 1884-1970
8,425 items
29 containers
12.6 linear feet
2 microfilm reels
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Artist. Correspondence and other papers including a large number of letters between Peirce and his mother, Anna Hayford Peirce, that trace the development of Peirce's artistic career and his mother's travels and her social life in Bangor, Maine.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Biddle, George, 1885-1973--Correspondence.; Colcord, Lincoln, 1883-1947--Correspondence.; Copeland, Charles Townsend, 1860-1952.; Gorsline, Douglas W., 1913-1985--Correspondence.; Hartley, Marsden, 1877-1943--Correspondence.; Hemingway, Ernest, 1899-1961--Correspondence.; Hooton, Earnest Albert, 1887-1954--Correspondence.; Ipcar, Dahlov Zorach, 1917- --Correspondence.; Lee, Doris, 1905-1983--Correspondence.; Morison, Samuel Eliot, 1887-1976--Correspondence.; Peirce family--Correspondence.; Peirce family.; Peirce, Anna Hayford, 1856-1928--Correspondence.; Peirce, Hayford, 1883-1946--Correspondence.; Peirce, Waldo, 1884-1970.; Perkins, Maxwell E. (Maxwell Evarts), 1884-1947--Correspondence.; Poor, Henry V. (Henry Varnum), 1812-1905--Correspondence.; Saint-Gaudens, Homer, 1880-1958--Correspondence.; Sheets, Millard, 1907-1989--Correspondence.; Taubes, Frederic, 1900-1981--Correspondence.; Van Loon, Hendrik Willem, 1882-1944--Correspondence.; Young, Art, 1866-1943--Correspondence.; Zorach, William, 1887-1966--Correspondence.
Organizations
Harvard University--Students.
Subjects
Art, American--20th century.; Art.; Voyages and travels.
Places
Bangor (Me.)--Social life and customs.; Maine--Social life and customs.
Occupations
Artists.
Provenance
The papers of Waldo Peirce, artist, were given to the Library of Congress by his widow, Ellen Larsen Peirce, in the years 1971-1973, 1978-1979, and 1986. Other papers were received as a gift of his son, J. Waldo Peirce, in 1965-1966 and of his daughter, Anna Peirce, in 1973.
Transfers
Drawings, water colors, and photographs have been transferred to the Library’s Prints and Photographs Division where they are identified as part of these papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Waldo Peirce are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Microfilm
A microfilm edition of part of these papers is available on two reels. Consult a reference librarian in the Manuscript Division concerning availability for purchase or interlibrary loan.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1884, Dec. 17 Born, Bangor, Maine
1908 A.B., Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass.
1910 1914 Traveled and studied art in France and Spain; attended Julian Academy, Paris, France
1912 Married Dorothy Rice (divorced 1918)
1915 1917 Served with American Ambulance Corps in France during World War I
1920 Married Ivy Troutman (divorced)
1921 1922 Lived in Tunis, Tunisia
1926 First American exhibition of his paintings
1930 Returned to the United States Married Alzira Boehm (divorced)
1944 Awarded first prize, Artists for Victory competition
1946 Married Ellen Larsen
1957 Named director of fine arts, Colby College, Waterville, Maine
1970, Mar. 8 Died, Newburyport, Mass.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Waldo Peirce (1884-1970) span the years 1889-1977 and consist of a diary, correspondence, writings, legal and financial papers, photographs, and miscellaneous personal items. The collection is organized into six series: Diary, Family Correspondence, General Correspondence, Miscellany, Formerly Restricted Family Correspondence, and Addition.
Much of the Family Correspondence and Formerly Restricted Family Correspondence is between Waldo Peirce and his mother, Anna Hayford Peirce, 1892-1928. Often illustrated with pen and ink drawings, the son’s letters trace Peirce's artistic career in vivid detail. Her letters describe life in Bangor, Maine, and the various countries that she visited. Also in the Family Correspondence are letters of Waldo’s brother, Hayford Peirce, an authority on Byzantine art and author of publications on late Roman, Byzantine, and early Islamic archaeology.
Prominent correspondents in the General Correspondence include fellow artists such as George Biddle, Douglas W. Gorsline, Marsden Hartley, Doris Lee, Henry Varnum Poor, Homer Saint-Gaudens, Millard Sheets, Frederic Taubes, Hendrik Willem Van Loon, Art Young, Dahlov, Zorach Ipcar, and William Zorach. Also prominent are letters from Ernest Hemingway (whom Peirce met in France during World War I and accompanied on several trips to Spain), Earnest Albert Hooton, Samuel Eliot Morison, and Maxwell E. Perkins. Of particular interest are letters he received from his close friend Lincoln Colcord, a literary critic and author of sea stories, for the period 1923-1944.
Included in the Miscellany are an incomplete draft of an autobiography, bills and receipts, drawings made by Peirce’s children and grandchildren, a holograph collection of his Rabelaisian poetry, and school papers from when he was a student at Harvard. Many of the latter are embellished with Peirce's pen and ink drawings, and some are further enhanced by the often acerbic comments of Charles Townsend Copeland.
Formerly Restricted Family Correspondence consists of letters received that were made available to readers without requiring special permission beginning in 1998. The Addition supplements previously processed series of family material, general correspondence, and miscellany.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in six series:
Diary, 1915-1916
Family Correspondence, 1892-1966
General Correspondence, 1909-1970
Miscellany, 1889-1969
Formerly Restricted Family Correspondence, 1910-1969
Addition, 1889-1977
Container List
- Diary, 1915-1916 (Box 1)
  Bound diary.
  - 1915-1916 (Box 1)
- Family Correspondence, 1892-1966 (Box 1-7)
  Letters sent and received by Peirce and various members of his family.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of family member.
  - Boehm, Chris (Box 1)
  - Boehm, Dwight (Box 1)
  - Boehm, Jerry (Box 1)
  - Boehm, Rebecca (Box 1)
  - Boehm, Tonia (Box 1)
  - Boehm, Verna (Box 1)
  - Felshiem, Alzira (Box 1)
  - Fisk, Robin (Box 1)
  - Neisser, Alison Juliet (Box 1)
  - Neisser, Hans P. (Box 1)
  - Neisser, Julie (Box 1)
  - Neisser, Mark (Box 1)
  - Neisser, Philip T. (Box 1)
  - Neisser, Toby (Box 1)
  - Peirce, Anna Hayford (Box 1)
    - 1892-1910, (4 folders) (Box 1)
    - 1911-July 1917, (7 folders) (Box 2)
    - Aug. 1917-1920, (7 folders) (Box 3)
    - 1921-1923, (8 folders) (Box 4)
    - 1924-May 1926, (8 folders) (Box 5)
    - June 1926-1928, undated, (4 folders) (Box 6)
  - Peirce, Carroll E. (Box 6)
  - Peirce, Dorothy (Box 6)
  - Peirce, Frances W. (Box 6)
  - Peirce, Hayford, 1911-1945, undated, (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - Peirce, Margaret W. (Box 6)
  - Peirce, Mellen C. (Box 6)
    - 1901-1907 (Box 6)
    - 1908-1936, undated, (2 folders) (Box 7)
  - Peirce, Mellen C., Jr. (Box 7)
  - Peirce, Polly (Box 7)
  - Unidentified (Box 7)
- General Correspondence, 1909-1970 (Box 7-19)
  Letters sent and received.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent. At the end of the series are bound volumes of mostly outgoing correspondence. Three of the volumes are available on microfilm, shelf no. 15,751.
  - Alphabetical file (Box 7)
    - Adams, James Donald (Box 7)
    - Aiken, Conrad (Box 7)
    - Anderson, Maxwell (Box 7)
    - "A" miscellany (Box 7)
    - Baker, Carlos (Box 7)
    - Barrows, Lewis O. (Box 7)
    - Beach, Warren (Box 7)
    - Beebe, Lucius (Box 7)
    - Benét, William Rose (Box 7)
    - Biddle, George (Box 7)
    - Blutenthal, Arthur (Box 7)
    - Brann, Louis J. (Box 7)
    - Brewster, Ralph O. (Box 7)
    - Brooks, Van Wyck (Box 7)
    - Bruce, Edward (Box 7)
    - "B" miscellany, (8 folders) (Box 8)
    - Calmer, Ned (Box 8)
    - Canaday, John (Box 8)
    - Capp, Al (Box 8)
    - Cary, Richard (Box 8)
    - Chafee, Zechariah, Jr. (Box 8)
    - Child, Richard Washburn (Box 8)
    - Ciardi, John (Box 8)
    - Colcord, Lincoln, 1923-1944, undated, (2 folders) (Box 8)
    - Collier, Constance (Box 8)
    - Conrad, Barnaby (Box 8)
    - Copeland, Charles T. (Box 8)
    - Crosby, Caresse (Box 8)
    - Crowninshield, Frank (Box 8)
    - "C" miscellany (Box 9)
    - Davis, Elmer (Box 9)
    - Dawson, Fred (Box 9)
    - Dodd, Lamar (Box 9)
    - Drury, Samuel S. (Box 9)
    - "D" miscellany, (3 folders) (Box 9)
    - Eastman, Max (Box 9)
    - Eisenhower, Milton S. (Box 9)
    - Ellis, Foster (Box 9)
    - "E" miscellany (Box 9)
    - Fadiman, Clifton (Box 9)
    - Fiedler, Arthur (Box 9)
    - Fulbright, J. William (Box 9)
    - "F" miscellany, (2 folders) (Box 9)
    - Gibbs, Wolcott (Box 9)
    - Gingrich, Arnold (Box 9)
    - Goddard, Paulette (Box 9)
    - Gold, Michael (Box 9)
    - Gorsline, Douglas W. (Box 9)
    - Griswold, Roger (Box 9)
    - Gruening, Ernest (Box 9)
    - Gruskin, Alan D. (Box 9)
    - "G" miscellany, (2 folders) (Box 10)
    - Hartley, Marsden (Box 10)
    - Hayes, Helen (Box 10)
    - Hemingway, Ernest (Box 10)
    - Hemingway, Mary (Box 10)
    - Hicks, Granville (Box 10)
    - Hooton, Earnest Albert (Box 10)
    - Hotchner, A. E. (Box 10)
    - "H" miscellany, (5 folders) (Box 10)
    - "I" miscellany (Box 10)
    - Jewell, Edward A. (Box 10)
    - "J" miscellany (Box 10)
    - Keaney, Frank (Box 10)
    - "K" miscellany (Box 10)
    - Lamont, Corliss (Box 11)
    - Lee, Doris (Box 11)
    - Limited Editions Club (Box 11)
    - Lowell, Robert (Box 11)
    - "L" miscellany, (2 folders) (Box 11)
    - McCord, David T. W. (Box 11)
    - McIntyre, Alfred R. (Box 11)
    - MacLeish, Archibald (Box 11)
    - "Mc" miscellany (Box 11)
    - Mack, Walter S., Jr. (Box 11)
    - Marquand, John P. (Box 11)
    - Matisse, Pierre (Box 11)
    - Meredith, Burgess (Box 11)
    - Moe, Henry Allen (Box 11)
    - Morley, Christopher (Box 11)
    - Morison, Samuel Eliot (Box 11)
    - Morse, Wayne (Box 11)
    - Moss, Arnold (Box 11)
    - "M" miscellany, (5 folders) (Box 11)
    - Nickerson, Osgood A. (Box 11)
    - "N" miscellany, (2 folders) (Box 12)
    - "O" miscellany (Box 12)
    - Perkins, Maxwell E. (Box 12)
    - Perry, Oliver H. (Box 12)
    - Peters, Rollo (Box 12)
    - Plaut, James S. (Box 12)
    - Poor, Henry Varnum (Box 12)
    - Powers, Walter A. (Box 12)
    - "P" miscellany, (3 folders) (Box 12)
    - "Q" miscellany (Box 12)
    - Rehm, George (Box 12)
    - Rehm, Mary (Box 12)
    - Roosevelt, Eleanor See Container 7, Bruce, Edward (Box 12)
    - Roosevelt, Franklin D. See also Container 7, Bruce, Edward (Box 12)
    - Rowan, Edward B. (Box 13)
    - "R" miscellany (Box 13)
    - Saint-Gaudens, Homer (Box 13)
    - Schwartz, Manfred (Box 13)
    - Sheets, Millard (Box 13)
    - Shurtleff, Harold R. (Box 13)
    - Sloane, William (Box 13)
    - Smith, Walter W. ("Red") (Box 13)
    - Spencer, Betty Lockett (Box 13)
    - Stokes, Anson Phelps, Jr. (Box 13)
    - Street, Julian (Box 13)
    - "S" miscellany, (3 folders); (2 folders) (Box 13, Box 14)
    - Taubes, Frederic (Box 14)
    - "T" miscellany, (2 folders) (Box 14)
    - "U" miscellany (Box 14)
    - Van Doren, Mark (Box 14)
    - Van Loon, Gerard Willem (Box 14)
    - Van Loon, Hendrik Willem (Box 14)
    - "V" miscellany (Box 14)
    - Weston, Christine (Box 14)
    - White, E. B. (Box 14)
    - White, Katharine S. (Box 14)
    - White, Paul Dudley (Box 14)
    - White, Wallace H. (Box 14)
    - Whitehill, Walter Muir (Box 14)
    - Williams, Oscar (Box 14)
    - Willingham, Calder (Box 14)
    - "W" miscellany, (1 folder); (3 folders) (Box 14, Box 15)
    - Young, Art (Box 15)
    - "Y" miscellany (Box 15)
    - Zorach, Dahlov (Box 15)
    - Zorach, William (Box 15)
    - Unidentified, (2 folders) (Box 15)
  - Bound file (Box 16)
    - Vol. 1, 1919-1933, 1940, undated (Box 16)
    - Vol. 2, 1931-1935, undated (Box 16)
    - Vol. 3, 1910, 1931-1943 (Box 17)
    - Vol. 4, 1935-1936 (Box 17)
      Available on microfilm, shelf no. 15,751
    - Vol. 5, 1936-1937 (Box 18)
    - Vol. 6., 1939 (Box 18)
    - Vol. 7, 1940-1941 (Box 19)
- Miscellany, 1889-1969 (Box 20-22)
  Bills and receipts, poems, school papers, and other items.
  Arranged by type of material.
  - Autobiography, incomplete draft (Box 20)
  - Bills and receipts, (3 folders) (Box 20)
  - Biographical information (Box 20)
  - Children's drawings (2 folders), (2 folders) (Box 20)
  - Last will and testament (Box 21)
  - Poems (Box 21)
  - Photographs (Box 21)
  - School papers, (3 folders); (2 folders) (Box 21, Box 22)
  - Printed matter (Box 22)
  - General miscellany, 1901-1955, undated (Box 22)
- Formerly Restricted Family Correspondence, 1910-1969 (Box 23-25)
  Family letters received.
  Arranged by name of family member.
  - Family correspondence (Box 23)
    - McCormick, Ada Peirce, 1910-1970, (2 folders) (Box 23)
    - McCormick, Fred C. 1923-1950 (Box 23)
    - Neisser, Anna Peirce, 1939-1968, (3 folders); (1 folder) (Box 23, Box 24)
    - Neisser, Ulric, 1954-1963 (Box 24)
    - Peirce, Alzita, 1930-1950 (Box 24)
    - Peirce, Catherine, 1968(?) (Box 24)
    - Peirce, Ellen, 1945-1961 (Box 24)
    - Peirce, Gareth, 1964-1966 (Box 24)
    - Peirce, Ivy Troutman, 1922-1964, (2 folders) (Box 24)
    - Peirce, Jonathan Waldo, 1952-1969 (Box 25)
    - Peirce, Karen Julia, 1957-1969 (Box 25)
    - Peirce, Mellen III, 1933-1963 (Box 25)
    - Peirce, Michael, 1933-1963, (3 folders) (Box 25)
- Addition, 1889-1977 (Box 26-29)
  Family correspondence, general correspondence, special correspondence, writings and miscellaneous material.
  Arranged by type of material and therein alphabetically by name of person, organization, subject, or title. Writings in Container 28 titled “Alphabets Intimes” and “Le Mariage de Suzanne,” written and illustrated by Peirce before World War I, are available only on microfilm, shelf no. 19,450.
  - Family correspondence (Box 26)
    - Bahr, Rebecca Boehm, 1967 (Box 26)
    - Hayford, Laura, 1908 (Box 26)
    - McCormick, Ada Peirce, 1931-1944 (Box 26)
    - Peirce, Anna Hayford (Box 26)
      - 1893-1927, (9 folders) (Box 26)
      - 1910-1927, typescripts, (2 folders) (Box 27)
    - Peirce, Ellen Larsen, 1958-1969 (Box 27)
    - Peirce, Jonathan Waldo (“John”), 1962-1968, undated (Box 27)
    - Peirce, Karen Julia, 1952-1962, undated (Box 27)
    - Peirce, Mellen C., 1912-1928 (Box 27)
    - Reis, Rachael Boehm, 1967 (Box 27)
  - General correspondence, 1910-1955 (Box 27)
  - Special correspondence (Box 27)
    - Bates College, Lewiston, Maine, 1966-1970 (Box 27)
    - Cambridge School of Weston, Mass., 1966 (Box 27)
    - Colby College, Waterville, Maine, 1968-1970 (Box 27)
    - Harvard University, Fogg Art Museum, Cambridge, Mass., 1932-1933 (Box 27)
    - Library of Congress, 1965 (Box 27)
    - Midtown Galleries, New York, N.Y., 1937-1970 (Box 27)
    - Museum of Fine Arts, Boston, Mass., 1932-1967 (Box 27)
    - Princeton University Library, Princeton, N.J., 1966 (Box 27)
    - Searsport, Maine, School Department, 1966 (Box 27)
    - University of Maine, Orono, Maine, 1965-1969 (Box 27)
    - Wise, Russell and Winnie, 1954-1977, undated
  - Writings file (Box 28)
    - Autobiography, chapter drafts (Box 28)
    - Booklets, “Alphabets Intimes” and “Le Mariage de Suzanne,” written and illustrated by Peirce before World War I
      Available only on microfilm, shelf no. 19,450
    - Reviews (Box 28)
    - Notebooks (Box 28)
    - Notes and sketches (Box 28)
    - Photograph albums, 1901-1939, undated, (4 vols.) (Box 28)
    - Miscellany (Box 28)
  - Miscellaneous records (Box 29)
  - Scrapbook (Box 29)